The late fourth century A.D. The Roman Empire began to crumble.
公元4世紀晚期 羅馬帝國江河日下
Alexandria, in the province of Egypt,
地處於埃及行省的亞歷山大港
still retained some of its lustre,...
如同落日余暉
...possessed one of the Seven Wonders of the ancient world:...
該港擁有古代世界七大奇跡之一
...the legendary lighthouse,
享譽盛名的亞歷山大燈塔
and the biggest library known.
以及人類早期歷史上最偉大的圖書館
The library was a not only cultural but a religious symbol,...
這個書館不僅是文化寶庫 也是宗教像征
a place where the pagans worshiped their ancestral gods.
多神教徒在此參拜他們的祖先神
The traditional pagan worship in the city now coexisted...
如今傳統的多神教徒與猶太教徒
...with the Jews,
在此共存
and an unstoppable religion up to now banned, ...
同處於此還有屢禁不止的
...Christianity.
基督教
How many fools do you think have asked themselves
少有傻瓜會捫心自問
why don't the stars fall from the sky
星星為何不會從天空墜落
But you, who've had the teachings of the wise,
可你不同 你受過智者的教育
You know that the stars move neither up nor down,
你知道星星只會升起或落下
and merely revolve from east to west,
自東至西轉動
following the most perfect course ever can seived,
沿著最完美的軌跡
the circle.
做圓周運動
Because the circle reigns in heaven,
圓周運動主宰宇宙
the stars have never fallen and they never will.
因而星星永不墜落
But what about here on Earth?
但是在地球上呢?
Here, bodies do fall.
在地球上 物體自由降落
But their movements are not circular but linear.
但是他們的運行軌跡 不是環形而是線形
Watch again.
再看一次
No, leave it.
別撿 放那兒
So,
那麼
What mysterious wonder do you would think
你們認為在地面之下究竟蘊藏著
might be lurking beneath the earth
何種神奇物質?
that would make every single person and animal
使得人類 動物
and object and slave settle there.
所有的物體以及奴隸適得其所
What might it be?
那會是什麼呢?
The heaviness, lady.
是重力 老師
No.
不對
Synesius.
辛奈西斯
Their weightiness.
因為他們的重量
No, you are both speaking about the same thing,
不對 你們說的是一樣東西
but you not talking about primary course.
但你們都沒有切中要害
Has any of you ever wondered at the thought that your...
你們有沒有人想過你們的
that your feet ...
你們的腳
are standing on the very center of the cosmos
站立在宇宙的正中央
that holds all things together,
而宇宙承載萬物
and pulls them together.
並將萬物緊密相連
If there were no center,
如果沒有中心
then the universe would be shapeless, infinite,
那麼宇宙將會混沌不清 無窮無盡
formless, chaotic.
無狀之狀 雜亂不堪
Well, it'll make little difference that
無論我們身處何方
if we were here, there or anywhere,
都將毫無二致
and we'd all be better off never having been born.
那我們不降臨人間豈不更好
God, our Father,
神 我們之父
lord of the universe,
乃萬物之主
origin of all things,
萬物之源
eternal force of the cosmos,
宇宙之永恆能量
where everything has its beginning and everything its end.
萬事萬物在此有始有終
All Mighty Serapis,
全能的塞拉皮斯《古埃及死神》
Isis
伊希斯《大地之母 生命之神》
Horus
荷魯斯《法老的守護神》
Anubis
阿努比斯神《守墓神》
And all the gods that give child protection
以及所有凡間與天上
both in heaven and on earth ...
給予子民保護的諸神
Something in the market.
市集上出事了
I know you also feel something as well.
我知道你對我也有感覺
I've seen.
我看出了
Tell the master that we're leaving.
請轉告主人我們要走了
Can you believe.
難以置信
He was courting me as if I was one of his conquests.
他像我示愛還把我當成他的戰利品
This Orestes is as foolish as his father.
真是有其父必有其子
If I had already suggested that he devoted his heart to another muse
如果我建議他移情至另一位
one more beautiful than I.
姿色更甚於我的女神
- Who?  - Music.
-誰? -繆斯可《Music 音樂》
Music
音樂
He didn't find it amusing.
他可沒像你笑得這麼開心
But how could 227 had become 16 ?
本來是227 怎會變成16呢?
Look at this, it's 14.
看這個 這裡是14
They behave like humans!
他們的生活習性與人類無異
They eat, drink and fornicate!
他們吃喝享樂 驕奢淫逸
If my gods eat, drink and fornicate,
如果我的諸神也吃喝享樂 驕奢淫逸
good for them.
豈不快哉
No this, no this
不是這樣的 不是
you who console yourself with pagan images.
你們崇拜的形像沒有一絲神聖可言
Men, women, birds, reptiles!
不管是男人女人 還是飛禽走獸
Serapis! Serapis!
塞拉皮斯 塞拉皮斯
Who could trust the God, with a flower pot for a crown?
誰會信仰把花盆當做皇冠的神呢?
Hey You, Christians,
你們這些基督徒啊
how arrogant you've become now
羅馬帝國讓你們幸存於此
that the Empire allows you to exist
你們卻變得如此狂妄自大
My father's father saw them
我的祖父曾看見他們
slaughtered at the circus and fed to the lions.
在競技場裡被屠殺並用來喂獅子
Enough! Enough! Watch.
打住,打住 看著
Watch.
看著
I shall now walk cross the fire.
我將穿越火坑
If my god ...
若我主是
If my God is the true god, I shall suffer no harm.
若我主是真神 我將會毫發無損
If however your gods exist,
然而如若你的主存在
they'll roast me like a pig.
我就會像只豬一樣被烤死
You ...
你
You're a man!
你真勇敢
You'll burn!
你會被燒死的
You will have what you deserve!
你會遭到報應的
Now let's see if you can walk cross the fire.
現在我們來看看 你是否能穿越火坑?
What are you doing?
你們想干嘛?
Stop, you can not do that! Let the man go.
住手 你們不能這樣 放開他
Be quiet, pagen!
閉嘴 多神教徒
Or we will pull you as well.
否則把你也拖進去
Whose is this?
這是誰的?
How many times must I repeat myself?
我得重復多少遍?
Today, the Christians burned a man
今天 基督徒當眾燒傷了一名男子
right in the middle of agora!
就在廣場中央
I will not have this in my house!
我的屋子裡嚴禁出現這種東西
Not in the house of Theon!
賽昂家嚴禁此物
Give it to me.
給我
Master, I beg your mercy if you let her go.
主人 望您開恩 對此既往不咎
- Davus!  - Get up.
-達烏斯 -起來
You have nothing to do with this.
這與你無關
I too, am a Christian.
我也是一名基督徒
What did you say?
你說什麼?
Punish me for the both of us.
連我也一並懲罰吧
So, now they presumed to teach us mercy
他們妄想教我們什麼是仁慈
- Get a whip.  - Father!
-拿鞭子來 -父親
Please wait until you calm, will you?
請您冷靜冷靜 好嗎?
Father, I beg of you. I beg of you
父親 我求您了 我求您了
Wrapped in... in a blazing brightness?
他真的被燃燒的光亮包圍嗎?
It was the flames, stupid.
傻子 那是真正的火焰
Then why did not he burned like the pagan?
那他為什麼沒有像多神教徒那樣燃燒?
Tell me.
告訴我啊
Leave us ...
請你回避一下
Come here.
過來
Then kneel.
跪下吧
Tell me, is that true you are a Christian?
你真的是一名基督徒嗎?
I do not know what to say, mistress.
我不知該怎麼說 女主人
Why not?
什麼意思?
If I said yes, that would be a lie
如果我說是 那就是欺騙您
If I had said no, it meant I lied to my master
如果我說不是 那就是欺騙主人
and I do not know which is worse.
我不知哪個情節更嚴重?
Then you should say nothing at all.
那你就該緘默不語
There.
好了
Thank you.
謝謝您
I want to know that the master is upset with himself about this.
我想讓你知道主人對此很失望
What is that?
那是什麼?
Something I made, mistress.
是我做的小玩意 女主人
But it looks like a ...
這看上去像是一個
What is it?
這到底是什麼?
It's Ptolemaic system.
這是托勒密的天體系統
Yes, it is.
的確如此
Did you make this?
這是你做的嗎?
Earth
這是地球
is the center of the cosmos.
她是宇宙的中心
And revolving around it
而環繞四周的有
the sun and the five wanderers:
太陽以及5大行星
Mercury, Venus, Mars, Jupiter and Saturn.
水星 金星 火星 木星 土星
Obstinately disobeying the law of the circle.
並沒有遵守圓周運行軌跡的規律
Nevertheless. Ptolemy shows us
然而托勒密卻向我們證明
that they do obey.
他們遵守圓周規律
The fact that we see them move in a loop
他們之所以繞圈運動
is due to the joint effect of two circles.
是由兩個天體環形運轉合力而為
One that travel around the Earth
其中一個繞地球旋轉
and another less circle proper to each wanderer.
另一個沿著較小的圓形軌跡自轉
Well, look, the epicycles
看 那是本輪
So you see is not heaven on the earth
你們所看到的並非真正的規律
but our eyes deceive us.
只是雙眼蒙騙了我們
Well said, Davus.
說的真好 達烏斯
I'd like you to know that your exposition shows me
你的講解證明
you are paying closer attention than one or two..others here
你比在座的某些人更加用心
I tell you The Gods should consulted to me
聽著 上帝在造物之前
before they created anything.
都應該先征詢我的意見
Why do you say that? Orestes
你這從何說起 俄瑞斯特斯
It all seemed so whimsical!
所有的這些都太古怪了
Why the joint effect of two circles?
為什麼是兩個天體 環形運轉合力而為呢
Would not it be more perfect if the wander is didn't wander
如果行星不按自己的本輪公轉
and the single circle gives sense to everything?
而只按一個環形軌跡公轉 不是更合理嗎
Orestes, by what authority did you judge the work of God?
俄瑞斯特斯 你有什麼資格 評判上帝的傑作
What is wrong with you, Christians?
我哪兒得罪你了嗎? 基督徒
Can a man no longer open his mouth in this city
難道人都不能開口說話了嗎?
You critisize creation,you critisize our Lords,
你批判天地萬物 你批判我們的主
and you offended us.
因而你冒犯了我們
You should move to the desert.
你該搬到沙漠裡去
You will not hear anything to offend you out there.
這樣你永遠都不會聽到這些逆耳之詞
You know nothing about what you speak. None of you.
你們不知所雲 所有人都如此
Synesius, What is Euclid's first rule?
辛奈西斯 歐基裡得的第一公理是什麼?
Why is the question?
你為什麼問這個?
If ...
那個
if two things are equal a third thing,
等於同量的量
and they are all equal to each other
彼此相等
Good.
很好
Now, are you both now similar to me?
你們都和我非常熟識吧
Yes
是的
And you, Orestes?
那你呢? 俄瑞斯特斯
Now I am actually saying this to everybody here in this room,
在此我向你們鄭重聲明
more things unit us than divide us.
我們要團結而不是分裂
Now whatever may be going on the streets, we are brothers.
無論外面事態如何 我們都親如手足
We are brothers.
我們親如手足
I want you to remember,
我希望你們記住
the bros of slaves and riffraff.
我們並非奴隸或者烏合之眾
Now  I think we should all honred Davus's with
現在我們用熱烈的掌聲
some very well end applause, so...
感謝達烏斯為我們講解這些知識
They'll judge us all alive and dead!
他們會決定我們每個人是生是死
And then it will be too late,
到了那個時候就為時已晚
because only those who believed in Jesus
只有那些信仰耶穌的人
will be saved.
才能得到救贖
What are you waiting for?
你們此時不皈依吾主
The Kingdom of God is upon us.
上帝之國在你我上方
Do you understand what I am telling you?
你們聽懂我說的話了嗎?
Yes
聽懂了
Do you understand like man do
你們明白嗎?要像個人
or do you not had, like sheep?
或者你們不明白 就像只小羊羔
What are you looking here?
你在這看什麼?
Yes, you.
對 就是你
Are you Ammonius,
你是阿摩尼阿斯嗎?
the man who formed the miracle?
那個創造奇跡的人
Do you want to see a miracle?
你想看到奇跡嗎?
Are you the one?
你是他嗎?
I am.
我是
Come with me.
跟我來
Jesus went throughout Galilee
耶穌走遍加利利 《馬太福音4:23》
teaching in their synagogues,
在各會堂裡教訓人
and preaching the good news of the kingdom
傳送天國的福音
and healing every disease and sickness among people.
醫治百姓各樣的病症
His fame went throughout all Syria
他的名聲就傳遍了敘利亞
and people came to see him worldwide.
來自世界各地的人們 都慕名前來朝拜他
That's Theophilus.
那是西奧勒斯
The bishop.
我們的主教
For theirs is the Kingdom of Heaven.
因為天國是他們的
Blessed are they that mourn
哀慟之人有福了
for they shall be comforted.
因為他們必得安慰
Blessed are the meek
溫柔之人有福了
for they shall inherit the earth.
因為他們必繼承土地
Blessed are those who have hunger and thirst for righteousness
飢渴慕義之人有福了
for they will be filled.
因為他們必得飽足
The word of God!
天主的世界
Blessed are the merciful
憐恤人之人有福了
for they will be find mercy.
因為他們必蒙憐恤
Blessed are the pure in heart,
清心之人有福了
for they will see God.
因為他們必得見神
The Lord be with you.
天主與你同在
With you too.
也與你同在
So how did you escape the flames?
你是怎麼穿過那火焰的?
- The Lord be with you. - And with you.
-天主與你同在 -也與你同在
What did you think? I pray!
你覺得呢?我祈禱而已
You probably do not even know how.
你可能都不知道該如何祈禱吧?
What do you have in your sack?
你那包裡有什麼?
- Do you have any food of you? - It is for my master.
-有吃的嗎? -這是我主人的
What's wrong with you?
你沒什麼毛病吧?
I have to pay for that with my own money!
給你的話,我就得自己掏腰包了
What do you need money for?
你要錢干什麼?
Look at the faces.
看看他們的眼神
Here.
來
I want you to try it yourself
我想讓你自己來試試
and afterwards I will teach you how to pray.
然後我教你怎麼祈禱
Come on
來
- The Lord be with you. - Bless you.
-天主與你同在 -主保佑你
See?
看見了嗎?
That is the miracle!
這就是奇跡
Go on, keep doing it.
繼續 接著發
The Lord be with you.
神與你同在
Please.
謝謝
Thank you.
謝謝你
Bless you,
神保佑你
God bless you.
主保佑你
Bless you.
保佑你
Hi slave
奴隸
What is your name?
你叫什麼名字?
Davus.
達烏斯
Davus the slaves!
奴隸達烏斯
You look like a true parabolan.
你像個真正的基督聖戰士
A true soldier of Christ.
一名真正的耶穌的戰士
What do they saying this?
他們說什麼呢?
Telling them to dance.
讓他們跳舞
The men are now happy with wine.
他們正暢飲美酒呢
All aboard!
出海旅行
What unfortunate!
多麼不幸的旅途
Save your servants!
救救你的奴僕吧
End the act two!
第二幕結束
Thank you, the audience.
謝謝觀看 各位觀眾
Excuse for the delay when we move things around
我們現在要更換道具以及演出服裝
and change our costumes.
希望大家諒解
Forgive me
不好意思
Forgive my boldness.
原諒我的大膽
I am Orestes,
我是俄瑞斯特斯
son of Orestes.
俄瑞斯特斯家的兒子
I am here. ..
我在這
I am here to declare my love for Hypatia, the philosopher,
我在這想說出 對哲學家希帕蒂亞的愛意
who no doubt know.
而她也深知這點
Some time, now following her counsel,
我采納了她給我的建議
I devoted myself to music
我投身於音樂當中
hope so seeking solace in the harmony of it sound.
希望在聲音的和諧中尋求到一絲慰藉
But for me,
但對我來說
such harmony resides only in my lady.
只有我傾慕的女士身上才有這種和諧
So,
所以
my purpose here is merely to
我站在這只是為了
offer my melody
獻上我的音樂
and I hope to ...
並且希望
Stop talking.
不用再說了
That man will go far. I tell you
那人肯定很有前途
If my prepared food for the banana not the fig,
如果我准備的是香蕉而不是無花果
I would have already falls that out his feet.
我早就扔在他腳下了
What did it to be best to present
你准備怎麼回禮呢?
Me?
我嗎?
How?
怎麼回禮?
Gratty, can you on your daughter's hand.
格來提 你能阻止的了你的女兒嗎?
Would don't you ever plan to marry her of?
難道你不打算讓她嫁人嗎?
Hypatia, subject to a man? Without read and to teach?
希帕蒂亞嫁給一個男人 不讀書不教書
Or even to speak her mind?
甚至不談她的那些想法嗎?
The most brilliant philosopher I know,
我認識的最傑出的哲學家
having to give up her science
必須要放棄科學
No, could be a death to her.
不 那會讓她生不如死的
That's true. Her work is admirable.
沒錯 她的工作受人敬仰
And she's wise and virtuous.
並且她德才兼備
But Theon,
可是賽昂
do not forget her situation.
別忘了她的處境啊
Being a Woman, I believe
她只是個女人
Our Father, who art in heaven, reveal bear
我們在天上的父 宅心仁厚
Don't let anyone else have her
別讓她答應別人
Please do not let anyone else have her
求你別讓她答應別人
Do not let anyone. Do not let anyone else have her.
別讓別人 別讓她答應任何人
Amen.
阿門
Good day, lady.
早安 老師
Good day.
早安
Yesterday many of you see
昨天很多人看到
one of your colleague present me with a nolos.
你們的同學把他的樂器獻給了我
I accepted the gift.
我接受了禮物
And today I wish to make him a gift of my own return.
而今天我也想回送給他一份禮物
This is for you.
這是給你的
It is the blood of my cycle.
這是我的經血
Orestes you...
俄瑞斯特斯你
you say you have found harmony in me.
你說你在我身上找到了和諧
Well I am suggesting that you look elsewhere
那我建議你看看周圍
because I think there is a little harmony or
因為我覺得周圍也存在著
or beauty in that.
和諧和美麗
Do you agree?
你覺得呢?
Yesterday we were discussing the Apollonius cone.
昨天我們談到了阿波羅尼斯錐
We speak of the circle, the ellipse, parabola.
我們講了圓形 橢圓 拋物線
- Today we see the hyperbola. - Lady!
-今天我們來講雙曲線 -老師
Forgive me, Lady.
不好意思 老師
Olimpios requires your present urgently to the serapeum.
奧林匹斯要你趕快到神廟去
You as well.
你們也是
Thank you, Lord. Thank you, Lord.
感謝主 感謝主
Thank you, Lord.
感謝主
Are we to enjoy them for speaking us the faith
難道我們要忍受他們詆毀我們的信仰
the custom the people until recently were coming out roles?
習俗 甚至我們的人民嗎?
- What happened? - It's dispicable!
-發生什麼事了? -這是種褻瀆
Christians have gathered in the agora.
基督徒已經在城市廣場集會了
They are mocking the gods.
他們在嘲弄我們的神明
We must put end to these insults!
我們必須阻止這些褻瀆
They may not fear him,
他們也許不怕他
but they will fear our swords!
但他們一定會怕我們的利劍
Wait!
等等
What is it you are going to do?
你們要干什麼?
Are you going to attack them?
你們要去襲擊他們嗎?
Are you going to stain your hands with blood for an insult?
只因為他們的無禮 就讓他們血濺當場嗎?
The gods! An insult to the gods!
是對神明們 對神明們的褻瀆
If you think it so outrate,
如果你覺得他們過分
just go and announce the act before the prefect.
應該直接去通知本地的提督
One might seem that you protecting them.
你好像在保護他們
I am try to protect our disciples.
我在盡力保護我們的學生們
You are inciting them to be wild murderers.
而你 在煽動他們成為野蠻的殺人犯
Theon, as director, you have the last word.
賽昂 作為首領 由你來決定吧
The insult must to be answered.
必須壓制他們對神明們的不敬
Those Jews among you can do as you pleased,
猶太教徒可以自願參加
this is not your battle.
這不是你們的戰爭
As for you, Christians,
而這裡的基督徒們
you would do well to join those of your own faith.
你們最好去找你們的耶穌
You will not caused my disciples out of this house!
你不能讓我的學生走出這個建築
- Glory to Serapis! - All for the gods!
-塞拉皮斯萬歲 -為了神明們
Wait for my command!
等我的命令
No one would suspect us until we have surrounded.
在我們包圍他們前 不會有人懷疑我們的
These swords are for the slaves! Slaves
這些劍是給奴隸的 奴隸們
Slaves are also summoned!
奴隸也要參加
Davus, go back.
達烏斯 回去
No. Go back.
不 回去
Kill the Christians!
殺了基督徒
Glory to Serapis!
塞拉皮斯萬歲
Let us listen to her now!
讓我們聆聽她的聲音
Do you hear her complain?
你們聽到她的抱怨了嗎?
No!
沒有
This one has lost her voice too!
這一座也失聲了
Their mouths do not speak,
他們的嘴不能說話
their eyes do not see,
他們的眼看不到東西
their nose does not smell.
他們的鼻子聞不到味道
Yet still a pagan come here they kneel before them!
但多神教徒卻要跪倒在他們面前
What madness is this?
這是多麼的瘋狂啊
By the gods!
順從神明們的旨意
Medoro!
梅多羅
God is one!
上帝只有一個
Death for the heathens!
打倒異教徒
You! What are you looking at? Get them! fight!
你 你看什麼呢?打啊
Fight!
打啊
Are you deaf? I said fight
你聾了嗎?我說打啊
I am a Christian!
我是個基督徒
- What is Christ? - Christ is one!
-什麼是基督? -基督是神
Death to the heathens!
打倒異教徒
God is one!
上帝只有一個
No! No!
不 不
The entrance, we must defend the entrance!
入口 我們必須守住入口
What's happening?
怎麼了?
Our men might be sent by the christians!
我們的人被基督徒打敗了
Father!
父親
It's all right. It's all right.
沒事 沒事
What happened?
怎麼了?
It was his slave.
是他的奴隸干的
Davus, give me some cloth and some water, quickly.
達烏斯 給我拿些布那些水來 快
Father ...
父親
Synesius, we must get out of here.
辛奈西斯 我們得離開這裡
Hold him still.
扶住他別動
Parabolans are coming!
基督徒們來了
God is with us!
上帝與我們同在
Hallelujah! Hallelujah!
哈利路亞 哈利路亞
- Close the gate! - No, no, our men are still out there!
-關上大門 -別 我們的人還在外面
May the gods protect them.
願神明們保佑他們
Close the gate. I say!
我說關上大門
Do not kill him! We will keep him a hostage,
別殺他 我們把他像那其它基督徒一樣
like the others. Did you hear that everyone?
留作人質 大家都聽見了嗎?
Any Christian that you catch
你抓到的所有基督徒
is now a hostage.
如今都是人質
Now, take our wounded to the temple and Christians
現在 把我們的傷者送去寺院
down into the cellars.
基督徒帶到地下室去
Anyone with a good eye and a good aim up on the walls.
眼神好的人去牆上觀察情況
Olinpios.
奧林匹斯
This one is a Christian.
他是個基督徒
Yes, and those three as well.
沒錯 還有那三個
If they are Christians, they will  go down to the cellars.
如果他們是基督徒 他們就得去地下室
Olimpios...
奧林匹斯
if you are going imprison my brothers,
如果你要囚禁我的兄弟們
you are going to imprison me with them.
你就得把我也關起來
If it is necessary, I will do that.
如果必須如此 我會這樣做的
If anyone,
如果任何人
anyone,
任何人
dare lay a finger on one of my brothers,
敢碰我兄弟們一根指頭
I swear I will run him through.
我發誓我會刺穿他的身體
Look!
看
Look at this!
看這個
Orestes.
俄瑞斯特斯
Thank you.
謝謝你
Since when there is
什麼時候開始?
so many Christians?
有這麼多基督徒的
We will have to negotiate.
我們不得不和他們談判了
What are we waiting for?
我們在等什麼?
What can we expect from a Christian emperor
一個基督徒君主能做些什麼呢
except we put up the sword
除非我們收起刀劍
I have settled for still being alive when it's worth to lives.
至少我現在活了下來
Care we'll do.
小心
No one should leave the group, please.
請大家都不要擅自行動
Are they going to pray all night?
他們要整夜祈禱嗎?
Davus.
達烏斯
Stay here.
待在這兒
It's safe here.
這裡很安全
Just stay here would be best.
好好的留在這吧
Synesius! What are you doing?
辛奈西斯 你要干什麼?
Lady, sister and mother,
老師 姐姐 母親
May God bless you and protect you.
願主祝福並保護你
Move back!
退後
Slave end up eating this
奴隸至死都吃這個
Slaves get to the back!
奴隸排最後
The three one come out
三個一出現了
It's a disaster.
會是場災難
Father, when will you leave the dice.
父親 你什麼時候才能不擲骰子?
You have been seen today?
今天有人看過傷口了嗎?
- No. - No?
-沒有 -沒有嗎?
Let's have a look.
讓我看一下
Promise me, my child,
孩子 向我保證
when I'm gone. You won't remember this foolish old man.
在我死後 忘記現在這個愚蠢的老頭
I promise.
我保證
Remember me as I was before.
記住我曾經的樣子
before when I could still think and
記住那個還能思考 並且
I work with you,
與你共事的我
and I listened to you.
記住我傾聽你心事時的樣子
How could I've been so wrong?
我怎麼會犯下這樣的大錯?
See. You here, locked up here because of me. ..
如今因為我的錯誤 讓你被困在這裡
Father, please.
父親 請別說了
I wanted you to be free.
我希望你能夠自由
I am free.
我是自由的
Hey Christians
基督徒們
What's that confindent for the God of yours doing now?
你們對上帝的那份自信哪兒去了?
Coffins for you, scum!
進棺材吧 人渣
So, tell me.
告訴我
Where are the Gods now?
那些神如今在哪裡?
Where are they?
他們在哪?
- Might as well look for others - Other?
-可能也去找別人了吧? -別人
Which one? The God of the Christians, perhaps?
哪一個?基督徒的上帝嗎?
Such boldness!
真是太放肆了
What do you think, Lady? You are so bold
你怎麼想?老師,你是如此的勇敢
Get the fire out.
把這盆火滅掉
You are indeed bold.
你的確很大膽
Very bold.
非常大膽
I've been thinking about something you said to me.
我一直在想你對我說過的那些事
Me?
我嗎?
The day that you criticize the heavenly mechanism
那天你質疑天體的運動軌跡
and you called it whimsical.
而且你把它稱為無稽之談
Yes, although..
是的 盡管
actually
其實
I was criticizing Ptolemy
我是在質疑托勒密的理論
for complicating everything with epicycles.
他的本輪理論讓一切都變復雜了
But I do not know. Perhaps, just simple minded.
但我不確定 也許只是有些欠考慮
No.
不是
The heavens
天空之上
should be simple.
應當是簡單的
So am I right or..?
那麼我是對了還是
What if ...
如果
what if there were a simpler explanation
如果有個更簡單的理論可以解釋
for the wanderers
那些行星又當如何?
There is.
有的
But it's so absurd, so old
但卻太荒謬了 太陳舊了
that no one gives it any credit.
沒有人願意相信它
What theory is that?
那是什麼理論?
Do you speak Aristarchus
你是在說阿裡斯塔克斯嗎?
Aristarchus maintained
阿裡斯塔克斯認為
that the earth moves.
地球本身在移動
The strange behavior of the wanderers
而幾大行星的奇怪行為
was nothing more than an optical illusion
僅僅是我們的星球
caused by our movement
在圍繞著太陽運動時
in combination with us around the sun.
所產生的光學幻覺而已
- A heliocentric model. - That's right.
-以太陽為中心的模型 -是的
The sun would be in the center,
太陽在中心
as Memphis dignity deals King of the stars.
仿佛它是宇宙眾星的尊貴之王
- And make us just..  - His work was lost
-讓我們變成了 -他的著作
be another wanderer.
另一個行星而已
in the fire that destroyed the Mother Library.
在主圖書館的一場大火中被燒毀了
This is why we have to take great care of this place.
這就是我們必須好好保護 這地方的原因
Our library
我們的圖書館
is all that remains of wisdom of men.
存留著人類的所有智慧
But every time you drop an object ...
但每次扔一個物體
Who speaks?
誰在說話
Forgive me mistress.
原諒我 女主人
I was listening.
我一直在聽
Speak up, Davus.
說吧 達烏斯
If the earth is moving,
如果地球在移動
every time you drop an object,
每當扔下一個物體
it would fall further behind.
它就會落到後面才對
And the wind would always blow against us.
而風應該會保持迎面吹來
And the birds would lose their way in flight.
鳥兒會迷失航向
I told you
我跟你說過
Aristarchus hypothesis make no sense at all.
阿裡斯塔克斯的假說一點都講不通
I feel that what you just said can be refuted.
我覺得你剛才說的可以被駁倒
But right now I do not know how.
但現在我不知道如何去駁倒
Make way for the prefect!
給提督讓道
Make way!
讓開
Listen everyone!
大家都聽著
Prepare to hear and obey the verdict of our emperor
請大家認真聽並遵守君主的裁決
I, Flavius Theodosius Augustus
我 弗拉維烏斯 狄奧多西 奧古斯都
emperor and supreme Head of the provinces of the Orions,
獵戶區省的君主和最高行政長官
having been informed
最近了解到
of the event notice recently in the place in city Alexandria,
在亞歷山大城發生的大事
hereby declare and command
特此宣布並命令大家
let the insurgents shall be protected and free...
這些起義者將會得到保護
In exchange for my generosity,
而作為我寬宏大量的交換
the insurgents will abandon
起義者必須馬上
the Serapeum and the Library immediately
離開神殿和圖書館
allowing the Christians to enter
同時允許基督徒進入
and dispose of the promsis
並處理掉所有卷軸
whatever you like.
按其心意
What are we expect? They destroy everything!
我們在期待什麼?他們會毀掉一切的
Pagans will leave by the stable!
多神教徒將會從後門離開
The Books.
那些書
From there you will be escorted to your home.
從那裡你們會被護送至你們的家裡
Obey within instance!
馬上執行
Send half a regiment to the other side.
派一半軍隊去那邊
Send the rest later.
其余的等會過去
Yes, sir.
是的 長官
Prefect.
提督
We won't be able to contain this muff for long.
我們們這樣堅持不了多久
On the cross! On the cross!
以十字架的名義 以十字架的名義
Let the lesser works!
留下那些次要的書
- What are the lesser works? - Just take important ones!
-哪些是次要的? -拿走那些重要的
The soldiers are retreating!
士兵們後撤了
Slave
奴隸
- Have you seen my mistress? - Just get over here and help!
-你們看到我的女主人了嗎? -快過來幫忙
- We can not carry so many! - We need more help.
-我們拿不了這麼多 -我們需要更多幫助
Please go and get my father out of here.
請帶我的父親離開這裡
Get him out of here now.
快帶他離開這裡
Slave
奴隸
Come on! Go, go!
快 快走 快走
Come on, quickly!
快點 快點
Hypatia and her students are still in the atrium.
希帕蒂亞和他的學生還在正廳裡
Are they out of their minds?
他們瘋了嗎?
If that's what they want, let them burn.
既然他們想那樣 就隨他們去吧
Come on!
快點
Lady.
小姐
Where have you been? Pick up that sack.
你去哪兒了?把那個袋子撿起來
- Lady We have to go. - Pick up the sack
-小姐 我們得走了 -把那個袋子撿起來
Why slaves never around when you need it.
為什麼到需要的時候 奴隸總是不在身邊
- I was ... - Move move you feet, quickly!
-我剛才在 -快點走啊 快點
Idiot!
白痴
Run!
快跑
Come on! There's no time!
快點 沒有時間了
Lady!
老師
We gotta go. You have to leave them.
我們得走了 別管這些了
God is one!
上帝只有一個
Hurry!
趕快
Davus!
達烏斯
Where are you going?
你要去哪兒?
- We have to go! - Davus, where are you going?
-我們得走了 -達烏斯 你要去哪兒?
If he want to die for our Gods, let him.
如果他想為我們的神而死 就隨他吧
Davus, no, please do not do this.
達烏斯 不要 不要這樣做
- Come on! - Davus!
-快點 -達烏斯
- Davus, no! - Come on!
-達烏斯 不要 -快走
By the cross
以十字架的名義
Hallelujah, hallelujah, hallelujah!
哈利路亞 哈利路亞 哈利路亞
Slave
奴隸
Davus!
達烏斯
Davus the slave!
奴隸達烏斯
Help me with this!
幫我弄倒這個
Help!
幫我
Hallelujah, hallelujah, hallelujah!
哈利路亞 哈利路亞 哈利路亞
Pagan scum!
多神教徒的人渣
The most of wound is history.
最沉重的傷痛都過去了
I know.
我知道
Davus.
達烏斯
You are free.
你自由了
Go.
走
From now on, in Alexandria
從現在開始 在亞歷山大
only Christian and Jewish worship should be permitted.
只許舉行基督教和猶太教的慶典
Pagan sacrifices,
禁止一切多神教的祭祀
worship of pagan symbols
禁止膜拜多神教的像征物
and visits to pagan temples should no longer be allowed.
禁止參觀多神教教堂
If anyone commits such acts or dare look at the statues
任何人敢這麼做或注視它們的
of their ancient gods, he shall be punished without mercy.
古老神像 都將會得到嚴厲的懲罰
After taking the library, many pagans were converted...
圖書館淪陷後 許多多神教徒皈依基督教
Hipatia continued teaching and researching,...
希帕蒂亞則繼續教學和進行研究
...while his former students held...
而他之前的學生
...important positions in the social elite.
成為了社會的中流砥柱
The empire was split in two forever.
整個帝國被一分為二
Many Christians saw this as a sign of the end of the world...
許多基督徒認為 這是世界終結的前兆
...and decided to prepare by practicing a more holy life.
於是決定過更神聖的生活
The order of "Parabolanos" Monks was charged to go...
基督教聖戰士穿梭在大街小巷
...through the streets and watch for Christian morality...
精力充沛地監督基督徒的品行
...now uneven by the presence of the Jews.
而猶太教徒的存在讓他們無法釋懷
Damn Jews!
該死的猶太人
They're just a bunch of good-for-nothing thugs, bad animals.
他們只是一群沒用的惡棍 畜生
Joran, my dear friend, calm down.
喬瑞恩 我親愛的朋友 冷靜點
Let Bishop Cyril speaks his own defense.
讓西裡爾主教解釋一下吧
Prefect
提督
our blessed parabolans,
我們那些神聖的聖戰士
Hung he has just called
他們僅僅是
piece of burden,
在打拍子而已
devote themselves truly enough to carrying burdens
只是為了附和他們打拍子而已
crippled, sick,the lever ...
他們都是殘疾人或者病人
And stones!
還有石頭
Prefect, they can carry stones.
提督 他們帶了石頭
And now they burst into the theater
突然衝進劇院
and they stoned us knowing we'll do nothing to defend ourselves,
他們知道我們無法自衛 還用石頭砸我們
because it is the Sabbath!
因為今天是安息日 《不能使用任何工具》
On the Sabbath you should honor God
在安息日這天 你們應該
in your synagogues instead of stuffing yourself
在猶太教會堂向主祈禱
with sweet set of the theater.
而不是在劇院欣賞戲劇
That is why the stones fell upon you.
正因為這個石頭才會落到你們頭上
Prefect, you hear that? Now he's threatening us. This is too much
提督 聽到了嗎? 他威脅我們 這太過分了
Friends, there are more things that unite us than divide us.
友愛些,我們是合眾院
We are brothers! We are all brothers
我們是兄弟 我們全都親如手足
Where would you Christians be without the Jews?
沒有猶太人哪會有你們基督徒?
Jesus was a Jew!
耶穌就是猶太人
There is something I find
我發現了點東西
stubbing what you told me.
可以反駁你所說的
- What? - Well
-是什麼? -好吧
Well, why Cyril begin cleaning up the city?
西裡爾為什麼要開始清理城市?
Is he not satisfied with what he already has?
他已經擁有這麼多了還不滿足嗎?
I think he's just trying to frighten the Jews.
他只想嚇嚇猶太人
But why say it in front of you
可為什麼要當你的面說?
What if really he was addressing.. you and not them?
如果他想對付的是你 而不是他們怎麼辦?
Me? Why? I'm as Christian as he is.
我 為什麼?我和他一樣都是基督徒
Yes, but you forget
是的 可你忘記了
that many of us from your circle are not.
你圈子裡許多人不是基督徒
A full sail, prefect.
滿帆 提督
Let's go.
走吧
- Aspasius, are you ready? - Yes, mistress.
-亞斯巴修 准備好了嗎? -是的 女主人
I would like you to take the sack and climb to top the mast.
我要你拿著麻袋爬到桅杆的頂端
And now, Lady,
好了 老師
will you finally tell me what the point of all these is?
你能給我解釋一下 這是怎麼回事嗎?
When Aspasius drop the sack,
亞斯巴修扔下麻袋的同時
the boat will be moving forward.
船在往前走
Therefore, the sack
因此麻袋
not fall at the foot of the mast,
不會掉在桅杆下
but will fall further back. I wouly say about ...
而是會掉得往後一些 我想大概
about here.
大概會在這兒
And what's so special about that?
這樣做有什麼意義嗎?
- Yes! - But You're wrong!
-太好了 -可你錯了
Yes, but this is definitive prove. It's definitive.
是 但這是決定性證據 決定性的
The sack behaved as if the boat was stationary.
麻袋就像是在靜止的船上那樣掉下來
What does that mean?
那意味著什麼?
I don't know.
我不知道
But the same principle can be applied to the Earth.
但同樣的原理也可以應用在地球上
It could be moving around the sun without us realizing.
它可能繞著太陽轉而我們卻不知道
- Aristarchus. - Exactly.
-阿裡斯塔克斯的理論 -沒錯
Why do you so mean to yourself for that, Lady?
你為什麼要那麼執著呢?老師
Ptolemy is not perfect,
托勒密理論雖不完善
but it works.
但卻很管用
Orestes, but you are the one who
俄瑞斯特斯 當時是你提出的
A few years ago you weren't so pragmatic, prefect.
提督 幾年前你可沒有這麼務實
A few years ago I spoke first and thought later.
幾年前我總是不經思考就發言
I have Cepheus third.
我看到了仙王座三
37.
三十七
48.
四十八
Venus and Mars share house in Aquarius.
金星和木星共同落在水瓶座裡
My father would have celebrated such a conjunction with a good wine.
我父親定會用美酒慶祝這種結合
- The stars will not fall. - Really?
-星星永遠不會落下 -真的嗎?
No, because they are fixed to the lid of the chest.
是的 因為它們都鑲在盒蓋上
The lid opens two hearts and then Jesus will appear.
蓋子會打開兩顆心 然後耶穌就誕生了
What chest for you talking about?
你說的是什麼盒子?
Do not you know that the universe is a gigantic chest?
你不知道宇宙是個巨大的盒子嗎?
Heaven is the lid on top and the Earth grounded.
天堂是蓋子 地球是底部
They haven't told this fool that the Earth is round!
他們沒告訴這個笨蛋地球是圓的
The Earth is flat.
地球是扁的
Your head is flat.
你的腦袋是扁的
Read the Scriptures!
去看看聖經吧
If the earth is round,
如果地球是圓的
why don't the people live on the bottom fall off?
為什麼住在下端的人們不會掉下去?
What about the ones on the sides?
住在側面的人呢?
Why don't they slide off?
他們為什麼不會滑下去呢?
Think about it.
想想看
Davus knows.
達烏斯知道
Hi Brother.
兄弟
What do you say?
你有什麼看法?
Is the earth flat or round?
地球是扁的還是圓的
Only God knows these things.
只有上帝才知道這些
Leave them on the ground!
放在地上別動
Leave them on the ground! It is where they belong!
別管它們 它們就該放地上
Lady, you must not disheart.
女士 請您不要灰心喪氣
Today on the boat you make great progress.
今天在船上您已經取得了很大的進展
Why do the wanderers vary that brightness
為什麼所有行星的亮度的變化
so unexpectedly?
會如此變化無常
And what is worse,
更糟的是
why does the sun...
為什麼太陽
why does it change size from summer to winter?
為什麼它的體積在夏天和冬天會不同
Perhaps because sometimes it is nearer
也許是因為它有時近
and other times it is farther away?
有時遠
But Aspasius,
可是 亞斯巴修
watch.
看
According to Aristarchus, the sun must be
按阿裡斯塔克斯的理論 太陽一定
at the center of everything.
是在萬物的中心
With us, the Earth,
而我們的地球
traveling in a circle around it.
繞著它沿圓周軌跡在公轉
Therefore, and this is the key
因此 這就是關鍵
We are always at exactly
我們和它一直
the same ...distance.
保持著同樣的距離
Now if, as what you just said, we accept the changes in distance,
如果按你說的 距離會改變
then we will force to add
那麼我們就得
an epicycle to the Earth orbit.
在地球軌道上加一個本輪
So it's going to be nearer then it's going to be farther away.
這樣它才會時近時遠
But now we fall in the same trap as Ptolemy.
這樣我們就陷入托勒密的謎團裡了 .
- Circles upon circles. - Exactly!
-圈套著圈 -沒錯
So I just don't know how to resolve this conflict.
我不知道如何解決這個矛盾
Let me know you think we can do this
你覺得我們能解決
Displace the sun from the center. Well,
把太陽從中心移走 那麼
not to have a center
並非必須在中心
breaks my heart, Aspasius.
這讓我感到傷心 亞斯巴修
So, tell me what do I do?
告訴我 我該怎麼做?
Rest, lady.
休息一下吧 女士
Parabolans!
基督聖戰士
- Parabolans! - What happens?
-聖戰士們 -怎麼了?
Parabolans, quick! Help!
聖戰士們 快來救命啊
San Alejandro is on fire!
聖亞裡罕德羅著火了
It is a fire.
著火了
Come on!
快點
Gather water! Get the bucket! Take this!
去提水 拿上水桶 拿著這個
- Quick! - Go! Go!
-快點
Quick!
快
Hurry up! Move, move!
快 快點 跑快點
Parabolans!
聖戰士們
Parabolans, quick!
聖戰士 快啊
Where's the fire?
哪著火了?
Over there! Over there!
在那邊 那邊
Jews! It's a trap.
是猶太人 這是陷阱
It's a trap!
這是陷阱
Christians all
基督徒們
last night was the night deplorable.
昨夜是悲慘的一夜
Now I say to you,
現在我告訴你們
grave no longer for our dead brothers.
不要再為死去的兄弟們感到悲傷
Weep not.
不要哭泣
Shed you tears for the others,
把眼淚留給其它人吧
for they are executioners.
他們是劊子手
Yes, yes.
沒錯 沒錯
Weep for them, for those who have done this,
為那些干這件事的人哭泣吧
they know none of God,
他們對上帝一無所知
none of love, none of pity.
沒有愛 沒有同情心
They know not.
他們什麼都不懂
Because in this day who repeated the world of Scriptures
因為今天他們重現了聖經裡的情景
with no understanding at all.
卻對此一無所知
It is they who saw only a man
他們只看到一個人
when the Son of God was standing in the front of them.
那就是上帝的兒子 站在他們面前
And it is they who in their blindness
也正是他們愚昧地嘲笑他
mocked Him and crucified him.
還將他釘死在十字架上
Yes, weep! Weep! Weep for the Jews,
哭泣吧 哭泣吧 為猶太人哭泣
those evil butchers of our Lord.
他們害死了我們的主
Because God ...
因為上帝
God has already condemned them.
上帝已經責罰他們了
It is God's will..
這是上帝的旨意
that they live as slaves,
讓他們成為奴隸
cursed and exiled until the end of time.
被詛咒 被流放 直到世界末日
Cursed and exiled!
被詛咒 被流放
Lady, do not stop, Lady.
女士 別停下 女士
Now all the Jews want to retaliate!
所有的猶太人都想要復仇
I'm afraid you do not understand what is really happening.
恐怕你不清楚目前的狀況
When this is over, there would be no more Jews in Alexandria.
一切結束後 亞歷山大 就不再有猶太人了
I am sorry to burst in like this.
很抱歉這樣冒失地闖了進來
Lady, you should not risk coming here.
老師 你不該冒險來這裡的
Where are the troops?
軍隊在哪?
Why are there no more soldiers on the streets?
為什麼街道上沒有士兵?
No army can contain entire city in that frenzy.
在那種混亂中 沒有軍隊 可以控制整個城市
He's calling for the annihilation of women and children
他要求殺光所有的婦女和兒童
A bishop!
他是主教
- A Christian! - Then lock him up.
-他是基督徒 -那就把他關起來
Prefect, you should have him arrested.
提督 你應該逮捕他
It's not so easy.
事情沒那麼簡單
Lady, Cyril knows we both share the same faith.
女士 西裡爾知道我們有相同的信仰
That place our prefect in the very awkward position.
這讓我們的長官進退兩難
If he defends the Jews,
如果他為猶太人辯護
half the city will rise against this government.
會有一半的市民反對政府
I see.
我明白了
If you choose to do nothing though,
可如果現在你什麼都不做
I believe Cyril will continue to do the same thing
我相信西裡爾 會繼續重復相同的事
over and over again until there is no one left in this city,
直到殺光城裡的最後一個人
no people for this government to govern.
就沒人可以讓政府管理了
How naive with me.
我太幼稚了
How naive with me to think with a final change.
我真幼稚 居然寄希望於最終的改變
Jews out!
猶太人滾出去
First they kill them
他們先殺了他們
and they buried them.
然後埋了他們
The Bishop of Cyrene.
是昔蘭尼的主教
- What is he doing here? - I'll find out.
-他來這兒干什麼? -我去看看
It's my little library of Alexandria.
這是我的小亞歷山大圖書館
This is where I teach children.
我在這裡教孩子們知識
An Apollonius cone.
阿波羅尼斯圓錐體
Yes, I built it to teach them about the four curves.
是的 我用它來教孩子們四種不同曲線
Circle,
圓形
the ellipse ...
橢圓形
Orestes should be here by now.
俄瑞斯特斯應該早到了才對
The parabole
拋物線
and hyperbola.
雙曲線
It's truly beautiful.
真是美極了
You know I often look at it and wonder
我常看著它去思考
why the circle co axis
為什麼相同的圓軸?
is such impure shapes.
會產生如此多不同的形狀
What I get to sit here and listen to you again
不如我坐在這裡再聽你講一次課
I bored you.
看來讓你無聊了
It's been a long time since I've done anything
我已經很久沒有教書了
but beat my head against system.
只是在研究天體系統上絞盡腦汁
And how they're more important matters a hand.
然而卻無人關注它的重要性
Forgive me.
抱歉 我來晚了
Two Christians in the hands of a pagan.
一個多神教徒控制著兩個基督徒
It's an outrage!
真是不可容忍
- How many? - I do not know, but it will stink.
-這裡有多少? -不知道 但會發出惡臭
Ammonius
阿摩尼阿斯
Does God speak with you?
上帝跟你說過話嗎?
All the time.
你總是這樣
Ammonius this, Ammonius that. Ammonius...
阿摩尼阿斯這樣 阿摩尼阿斯那樣
Today he spoke to me
今天他對我說得極快
so quickly that I had to ask him slow down
非常快 我不得不請求他說慢點
Tell me something.
告訴我
Do you ever think we have mistaken?
你認為我們是錯的嗎?
Why?
為什麼這麼說?
I was forgiven,
我曾被寬恕過
But now, I can not forgive.
但現在 我無法寬恕別人
Forgive?
寬恕
Who?
誰?
The Jews?
猶太人嗎?
Jesus pared them on the cross.
耶穌在十字架上寬恕了他們
Jesus was God
耶穌是上帝
And only he can show such clemency.
只有他才有這種寬容心
How dare you to compare yourself to God?
你怎麼敢拿自己跟上帝相提並論
Brother.
兄弟
You're still alive.
我們現在還活著
Why?
因為什麼?
Because it was
因為
his will save us from the stones.
是上帝的旨意 讓我們沒被石頭打死
God wants us here, doing what we do.
上帝讓我們在此 行該做之事
Don't you believe in that anymore?
你不再相信這些了嗎?
My Lord ...
閣下
Cyril is very proud man.
西裡爾是個驕傲的男人
Agree to meet but will not discuss the Jews,
他同意會面 但只協商和平議題
only discuss peace.
不商討猶太人問題
Peace?
和平
My suggestion, as your humble adviser in this affair,
作為您卑微的參謀 我的建議是
is for you to accept.
請您接受提議
Let peace be for most.
和平是最重要的
- Lady, what do you think? - Well... I ...
-老師 你怎麼看? -我
I don't think it is very encouraging.
我覺得這個提議並沒有那麼好
Why would he want to come and see Orestes
為什麼他來見俄瑞斯特斯?
He want come to you.
他要來見你
Demands you meets in the Library
但需要你在圖書館和他見面
During the Sunday's service.
在星期天的禮拜中
In the Library? Why?
在圖書館嗎?為什麼?
Only Christians have been permitted
那次搶占之後
to entered there since it's tombed.
只有基督徒才能進入圖書館
It is a provocation!
這是挑釁
Allow me to suggest.
請允許我說幾句
If you consider your presence
如果你覺得你的到場
so essential
是如此的重要
Why not let yourself be baptized?
為什麼你不接受洗禮呢?《信奉基督教》
The majority of us here, beginning
我們中的大多數人 包括最高長官
with our prefect, have accepted Christ.
都已經接納了基督教
Why not the rest of you?
剩余的這些人為什麼不行呢?
It's only a matter of time and you know it!
這只是個時間問題 你們心知肚明
Really?
是嗎?
Is it only a matter of time?
這真的只是個時間問題嗎?
Well, excuse me,
請容許我說幾句
Honorable Member but as far as I'm away..
尊敬的元老 但據我所知
Your God has not yet proved
你們的上帝並不能證明他自己
Be more just or more mercyful than their predecessors.
比他的前任們更公正更仁慈
Lady.
老師
Is it really just a matter of time before I accept your faith?
讓我接受你們的信仰 真的只是時間問題嗎?
Why, then,
那是什麼?
Should this assembly
難道這次會議
accept the consult of someone who admittedly
要接受一個毫無信仰的人
believes in absolutely nothing?
提出的提議嗎?
I believe in philosophy.
我信仰哲學
Philosophy.
哲學
Just what we need
正是現在這種時候
in times like this.
我們所需要的東西
Enough!
夠了
All these years I've been studying.
這些年來我一直在研究
Absolutely no life for my own,
完全沒有了自己的生活
and I wonder
我想知道
- What was the point  - Forget about what was said today.
-我這樣為了什麼? -忘了今天那些話吧
Is this all life holds for me?
是生活困住了我嗎?
What else?
還能是什麼?
I doubt anyone can see you
我覺得沒人能看出
as a devoted wife
你是一位忠誠的妻子
and mother.
一位盡心的母親
I think ...
我認為
I think everyone in the city know the history of the handkerchief.
城裡的所有人都聽說了手帕的故事
So ...
所以
My father loved woman.
我父親也會喜歡女人
Even he ...
連他也不例外
Who've ever loved?
有誰不愛呢?
Except you,
除了你
Lebanons.
黎巴農斯
If I could just...
如果我能
just unravel this ...
解開這個謎團
Just a little bit more.
只需要再多努力一點
And just get a little closer to the answer, then
只要離答案再接近一些 那麼
then I would...
這樣 我就能
Then I would go to my grave, a happy women.
我就能安然入土
Why?
為什麼?
Why does that mean so much to you?
為什麼這些對你如此重要?
Right now,
就是現在
this every second, whole earth could be moving
就在這一秒 整個世界可能都在移動
and no one realized it.
卻沒有人意識到這些
Except you and me
只有你和我知道
Believe me Lady, it's best that no one does.
相信我 老師 幸虧沒人意識得到
Do you really not think it important?
你覺得這些真的不重要嗎?
I do not understand why
我不明白你為什麼
you insist on moving the ground we walk on.
堅信人們腳下的土地是移動的呢
You saw of yourself what happened on the boat.
你也看到了船上發生的
Yes I did,But that does not mean this sailing on the earth moves.
是的 但那也不能證明地球在移動
What if it does
如果確實是這樣呢?
Hypatia, look around you.
希帕蒂亞 看看你的周圍
Death
死亡
Horror
恐懼
Destruction.
毀滅
If the stars move in a Circle
如果地球真的在圓形軌道中移動
Why would they share their perfection with us
他們為什麼 不把完美分給我們一些呢?
So we don't move.
所以我們沒有移動
In a circle.
只是不在圓形軌道中
We do not move ...
我們不是按照圓形
for a circle.
運動的
We do not move in circles.
我們並非在圓形軌道中移動
Ever since Plato,
從柏拉圖開始
All of them: Aristarchus Hipparchus, Ptolemy,
所有人 包括阿裡斯塔克斯 希巴克斯 托勒密
They have all... tried reconcile their observations
所有人都試圖用圓形軌道
with circular orbits.
來解釋他們的觀察結果
But What if other shapes  hidden in the heavens
但如果在宇宙中隱藏著其它形狀呢?
Another shapes?
其它形狀
Lady, There is no purer than the circle,
女士 沒有任何形狀比圓形更完美
you taught us that.
這是你教我們的
I know, but suppose, just suppose
我知道 只是假設
That the purity of the circle
正是圓形的完美
has blinded us from seeing anything beyond it.
讓我們忽視了其它的一切
In the same way that glared sun blind us from actually seeing
就像耀眼的太陽讓我們
the stars.
看不見星星一樣
I must begin all over with
我必須重新
with new eyes. I must...
重新審視這個問題
I must rethink everything.
我必須重新思考一切
Everything.
所有的一切
Reading from the first letter Paul to Timothy.
從保羅寫給提摩太的第一封信開始讀
I desired therefore that everywhere
我願男人
men should lift up their holy hand in prayer
舉起聖潔的手 隨處禱告
Without anger or disputing.
無忿怒 無爭論
In like manner I desire women to
又願女人
dress modestly,
廉恥 自守
decency and propriety
以正派衣裳為妝飾
not with braided hair
不以編發
or gold or pearls
黃金 珍珠
or expensive clothes.
和貴價的衣裳為妝飾
- But with good deeds. - Why is he reading this passage?
-只要有善行 -為什麼讀這段?
I do not know, prefect.
不知道 首領
I assure you it's not the one we agreed upon.
但我肯定這不是事先說好的那段
Let the woman learn
女人要沉靜學道
in quietness and in full submission, I do not permit a woman
一味的順服 我不許女人講道
to teach, or to have authority over a man.
也不許他轄管男人
But to be
只要
in Silent
沉靜
This is the word of God!
這是上帝之言
Amen.
阿門
Jesus himself
當耶穌把自己的神聖遺產
knew this when he
托付給他的十二門徒時
he entrusted his holy legacy to twelve men.
他自己非常了解這些
Men.
全是男人
Not a woman among them.
沒有一個女人
And yet
但是
I know some in Alexandria
我知道亞歷山大有些人
they admire and even trust in words
他們仰慕某個女人並且對她的話
of a woman.
言聽計從
The philosopher Hypatia.
哲學家希帕蒂亞
A woman who declare,
這個女人曾公然表示過
in public, her ungodliness.
她對上帝的不忠
A witch!
她是個女巫
Dignitaries,
官員們
It is the time for you all to reconcile yourself with Christ.
你們現在應該全部信奉基督
This is the word of God.
這是上帝之言
Kneel before it and embrace its truth.
在聖經面前下跪 並接受真理吧
Kneel.
跪下
Is he not going to kneel?
他不准備跪下嗎?
Sinner
罪人
I am a Christian
我是基督徒
- I am a Christian! - No you are not!
-我是基督徒 -不 你不是
I'm as Christian as you are
我是和你們一樣的基督徒
Make way for the prefect!
給提督讓路
Make way!
讓路
I am a baptized Christian!
我是受過洗禮的基督徒
I'll kill you.
我要殺了你
I'm as Christian as you
我是和你們一樣的基督徒
How could such a thing be possible?
怎麼會發生這種事
The culprit has been executed .
罪犯已經被繩之以法了
I would like you to take me to the prefect immediately.
立即帶我去見提督
Lady, he himself gave the order
女士 他親自下令
for you to be confined to the house until further notice.
讓你待在家裡等進一步的通知
At the moment your presence on the street is not advisable
現在這種情況 我建議你 不要在街上出現
For what reason?
為什麼?
Cyril make serious accusation against you.
西裡爾對你進行了嚴厲的譴責
And then. ..
那麼
What is he accused me of?
他控訴我什麼罪名?
Ungodliness  .....
對上帝不虔誠
and witchcraft.
還有使用巫術
I see.
我知道了
Is something bothering you, Lady?
你在為什麼事而煩惱嗎?女士
No.
沒有
Why don't you tell me what's worrying you.
不如你來告訴我你在擔心什麼?
Prefect, why don't you bite on it.
提督 咬住這個
Speak.
說
The Bishop of Cyrene want to see you.
昔蘭尼的主教想見您
Leave, all of you.
所有人都出去
Prefect, the wound is still not ...
提督 傷口還沒處理好
Get out. Get out!
出去 出去
All of you! Out!
所有人出去
Without went well.
你們沒能殺死我啊
You think I had a part in this?
你認為我也參與這件事了嗎?
But I show my face here if I want to betray you?
如果我想背叛你 怎麼還會來到你面前
- Are you blind?  - Yes, I was blind.
-你是瞎了嗎? -是的 我是瞎了
It's my head
他一直想要的
he's wanted all along. It's me.
是我的頭 他想讓我死
That snick is after.
隨後就有了這次襲擊
This government!
這個政府
This city!
這座城市
Now listen.
聽著
- War is bringing. - I know.
-戰爭即將到來 -我知道
I know.
我知道
Then swear your loyalty to me.
那麼宣誓對我效忠吧
To the Empire. Do it.
向國家宣誓 快
Condemn him or get out.
要麼譴責他 要麼滾出去
I will do it
我會這麼做的
On my knees, if necessary.
如果有必要 我甚至會跪下來
And not only that.
而且不只如此
In a few days I can gather other
幾天之內 我可以召集其它省的主教
bishops from province and monks from desert all against Cyril.
和沙漠裡的修道士們來對抗西裡爾
First I must ask you a question.
但首先我要問你個問題
Orestes, do you believe in Jesus?
俄瑞斯特斯 你相信耶穌嗎?
Do I what?
你問我什麼?
- Do you believe in Jesus? - Do I what!
-你相信耶穌嗎? -你問我什麼?
Are you a true Christian
你到底是真正的基督徒
or did you like so many others, only convert
還是你像那些寥寥眾生 僅僅臣服於
- prospering politics? - Synesius.
-自己的政治生涯 -辛奈西斯
Why didn't you kneel?
你為什麼不下跪?
- What choice did I have? - Why didn't you kneel?
-我有什麼選擇? -你為什麼不下跪?
What choice did I have?
我還有什麼選擇?
Betray Hypatia?
背叛希帕蒂亞
Condemn her?
譴責她嗎?
Would you have done that?
你會那麼做嗎?
I would never offend God.
我絕不會冒犯上帝的
It was he. He is offending God. He is offending him.
是他 是他冒犯了上帝
He is twisting...
他在歪曲聖經
Twisting...is what he is using the Scripture ...
他在曲解聖經的意思
He read what is written.
他只是在宣讀聖經
How many women do you obey?
有多少女人可以對你發號施令
How many?
多少個?
How many do you admire and listen to you?
你仰慕的同時 又能聽你傾訴 的女人有幾個
Only
只有
one.
一個
Only one.
只有一個
The Scripture ...
聖經
The Scripture is correct
聖經是正確的
and it was in his hands.
只是由於在他的手中
Brother, don't you see?
兄弟 你還不明白嗎?
Don't you see the insult to God
你不明白你那樣做是在眾人面前
in front of everyone?
侮辱上帝嗎?
I do not know ...
我不知道
I do not know what I believe...
我不知道該相信什麼?
You have to tell him.
你必須告訴他
Don't tell me now, Orestes.
別跟我說 俄瑞斯特斯
Tell him you believe in what is written.
告訴上帝你相信聖經
- I believe... - Don't tell me. Tell Him
-我信奉 -別跟我說 去跟他說
Tell God.
告訴上帝
Kneel!
跪下
Many are those who remember
許多人至今都記得
today the miracles of our beloved brother performed in life.
我們摯愛的兄長曾創造的奇跡
Like the time he commanded himself to the Father and threw himself
比如那次他將自己托付給聖父
into the fire and wasn't even singed.
踏過火堆卻毫發無損
Ammonius
阿摩尼阿斯
Dead for bravely defending your faith in Christ,
因為英勇捍衛對基督的信仰而獻身
I proclaimed you a motter,
我追封你為
a saint.
聖徒
From now on you shall be known as
從此以後你將會被人們稱為
Saint Taumasius.
聖圖梅西斯
We want justice!
我們要討回公道
Justice!
公道
May God show us the way, my dear
願上帝指引我們 我親愛的
parabolan, little else can I say to you.
聖戰士們 我言盡於此
What about monks of Nitria?
尼帝亞的修道士有多少
Count to at least 500 of them. Plus
他們至少有500人 而且
500 of our men?
我們還有500人
You think that's enough. He's the prefect!
你以為這就夠了嗎?他可是地區提督
He has a whole army to protect him.
都有的軍隊都會保衛他
Listen!
聽著
Why don't we do something much more simple and effective?
我們何不找個簡單又有效的方法
What do you talking about?
你指的是什麼?
We can hurt what worries him the most
我們可以傷害他最關心的東西
How?
如何?
- That whore. - Who?
-那個婊子 -誰啊?
What if we dared to look at the world just as it is
如果我們敢於面對世界的本相會怎樣?
Let's shed for a moment every preconceived ideas.
我們先摒棄那些先入為主的想法
What shape would it show us? What shape.
它會是什麼形狀?什麼形狀?
You once said the problem lies in the inconsistency of the sun.
你曾說過問題在於太陽體積的不一致
Yes I did, good...good. Put it into words.
沒錯 我說過 很好 說清楚一點
The sun must be at the center since we revolve around it.
太陽一定要在中心 因為我們繞著它旋轉
And at the same time
與此同時
another position since our distance from it varies.
它又在其它位置 因為它離我們時遠時近
- Yes, exactly. - How?
-沒錯 正是如此 -怎麼會?
How could it occupy two position at once?
它是如何同時占據兩個位置的?
How could occupy two position at once?
怎麼同時占據兩個位置的?
Aspasius...
亞斯巴修
Yes, yes. There. And the other one here.
沒錯 沒錯 就是那兒 另一個放在這兒
Keep the same proportion.
保持相同的比例
Good, very good. Now tie this end to that torch.
很好 把那端栓在火炬上
Aspasius
亞斯巴修
I want you to imagine that this is the Earth
我要你把這個想像成是地球
and the each of flames represent
每把火炬代表
the two extreme positions of the sun in relation to it:
它距離太陽的兩個極限位置
in winter and in summer.
也就是冬天和夏天
What would happen if both of the positions were the two centers
如果這兩個位置都是同一個圓
of one in the same circle
的圓心會是什麼樣
But it is impossible, mistress.
這是不可能的 主人
Wait, what do we know about a circle?
等等 圓是什麼?
We know that the center of the circle
我們知道圓心
is always same distance to any point along its perimeter.
到圓周上任一點的距離總是相等
- Exactly. - Yes.
-沒錯 -是的
What if I divide the center into two
那如果我們把這個圓心分成兩個呢
but what I keep constant is
讓圓周上的點到
the sum of there two distances to their perimeter
這兩個圓心的距離之和保持不變
Okay, I'll show you. Watch. As I move this rod along
好吧 我給你演示一下 看著 當我沿著
the court, as one segment increases
這個圓周移動棒子 繩子的一部分增加時
the other segment decreases. And vice versa.
另一部分就會減少 反之亦然
Therefore the sum of the two is always
因此兩者之和
gong to beconstant. You see that?
保持不變 你明白了嗎?
Now what if we apply this to the movement of
如果我們把這個理論運用到
the Earth?
地球的移動之上呢?
What...
我們會
figure
得到
will be...obtained ?
什麼圖形呢?
An ellipse!
一個橢圓軌道
With the sun at one of its foci.
太陽在它的一個焦點之上
Because,
因為
what is the circle execept
這種橢圓軌道
the very special ellipse
除了它的焦點太近以至於
whose foci have jonted so close together that they appear to be one
看上去似乎合二為一了 還能是什麼別的
Perhaps I'm completely raving, Aspasius.
或許只是異想天開而已 亞斯巴修
I mean really why should this be so? Maybe I'm just .. ..
為什麼非這樣不可 也許我只是
Maybe I'm...
也許我
What do you think?
你怎麼看?
It could very be so, mistress.
很可能就是這樣的 主人
Right, well, we will continue with this tomorrow.
太好了 我們明天再繼續
Get some sleep.
去休息吧
- Good night, mistress. - Good night.
-晚安 主人 -晚安
Thank you.
謝謝你
Davus!
達烏斯
What are you doing?
你在干什麼?
Lady.
老師
Let me see.
讓我看看
Why do not you sit down?
你去那邊坐下吧
Where is everybody?
大家都去哪了
Please sit down.
請坐
I have...
我有
I have news for you, too.
我也有消息要告訴你
All dignitaries
所有的已經皈依
who yet embraced to Christian faith
基督教的官員們
are to be baptized
將要在公眾面前
in public.
接受洗禮
The aim is very clear:
目的非常明確
to add to our course. All the Christians in the city,
為了增加擁護者 使市裡所有的基督徒
decent folk, prepare to
以及正派人士們
fight for me.
都為我盡忠
You speak of peddling faith.
你指的是宣揚信仰嗎?
Okay.
好吧
Very well.
非常好
Since everything seems to be decided already,
既然所有的事都已成定局
I didn't understand why you required my presence here.
我不懂你還讓我來這裡做什麼?
I'm not a member of the government.
我又不是政府的一員
No, you're more than that. You are the person that I trust most,
你不是 但你更重要 你是我最信任的人
and everyone knows it.
眾人皆知
What you are saying?
你在說什麼?
Lady.
老師
Years ago...
很多年前
Years ago you taught us something.
很多年前你教導我們
If...
如果
If two are equal to a third,
等同於同量的量
they are all equal to each other. Do you remember?
彼此相等 還記得嗎?
Yes.
是的
The three of us, we are all good people!
我們三個 我們都是好人
And you... you are as Christian as we are!
所以 你和我們一樣 都是虔誠的基督徒
Synesius, you don't question what you believe.
辛奈西斯 你對你的信仰深信不疑
I can not.
但我不能
I must.
我必須懷疑
That's a pity,
那真是太遺憾了
Lady.
老師
A great pity.
莫大的遺憾
Our revered teacher
我們所尊敬的老師
take it away from what she has herself taught us.
竟然背棄了自己曾教給過我們的東西
Or do you think I'm not aware the insane thing that you're involved.
你以為我不知道你 所執迷那些愚蠢的事...
- Synesius! - The Earth revolves around the sun.
-辛奈西斯 -地球圍繞太陽旋轉
What next? Lady, what next?
接下來又會是什麼?老師
I beg of you, just let me go.
求你讓我離開吧
Let me in! Let me in!
讓我進去 讓我進去
- I need to speak to her! - A parabolans?
-我有話對她說 -一個聖戰士
- Lady! - Go away before we arrest you.
-主任 -在我們逮捕你之前快滾
- Leave! - Aspasius
-走開 -亞斯巴修
It's me. Davus. Davus! Get of it.
是我 達烏斯 達烏斯 放開我
- Tell them who I am! - Do you know this man?
-告訴他們你認識我 -你認識他嗎?
Yes, what do you want?
是的 你想干嘛?
I need to speak to her. Where is she?
我有話對她說 她在哪?
- My Mistress is not here. - It is urgent! Where is she?
-女主人不在家 -十萬火急 她在哪?
- Where? - The prefect palace!
-哪裡? -她在提督宮殿裡
- The prefect palace. Yeah, thank you. -Get out of here.
-提督宮殿 -好 謝謝 快點滾
Who was that?
那到底是誰?
He was a slave once .
他以前是這兒的奴隸
Wait, please! Wait. I beg you
等等 求你 等一下 求你了
If you don't agree, I won't be able to protect you any longer.
如果你不同意的話 我就不能再保護你了
...I won't be able to have dealings with you.
我也不能和你交往
Or even greet you.
甚至不能和你打招呼
Hypatia.
希帕蒂亞
Don't you see?
你還不明白嗎?
I can not go on without you.
沒有你我活不下去的
I can not.
我不行
Without you I can't defeat Cyril.
沒有你我無法打敗西裡爾
Oh, Orestes.
俄瑞斯特斯
Cyril has already won.
西裡爾已經贏了
Thank you.
謝謝
But I do not need you.
但我不需要你們的保護
Davus!
達烏斯!
Brother! Where are you going?
兄弟 你要去哪裡?
We found her!
我們找到她了
Whore, walk!
婊子 快走
Move, sinner!
快走 罪人
- Whore! - Pagan scum!
-婊子 -多神教的渣子
Witch!
妖女
Pagan scum!
多神教的人渣
Move! Come on!
走啊 快走
Witch!
妖女
Strip her naked!
把她扒光
Get up.
站起來
That's it .So the God can behold you in all your filthy, whore.
就這樣 這樣上帝 可以看清你的污穢 妖女
the way you knock the prefect, whore...
看清你如何蠱惑提督 娼婦
Pagan!
異教徒
Whore.
娼婦
Look,
看啊
She's not reacting.
她一點反應都沒有
She's scream all right with the skin on a knife.
把刀子插進她的皮膚她就叫得出來了
- How many of you have a knife? - No
-有多少人有刀子 -不要這樣
Don't stain your hands with impure blood.
不要讓不潔的血液玷污你們的雙手
Let's stone her!
用石塊砸死她吧
- Let's stone this Witch! - Get some stones.
-我們用石塊砸死這個妖女 -去找些石塊
- Quickly! The ones we threw Orestes,
-快點 我們扔俄瑞斯特斯的石頭
they're still here.
還在這裡
I'll stay with her.
我看著她
She fainted.
她暈過去了
The body of Hipatia was mutilated and the remains...
希帕蒂亞的屍體殘缺不全 留下的部分
...were dragged through the streets and burned in a fire.
被拖去游街 焚燒
Orestes was outlawed forever and Cyril...
俄瑞斯特斯被永久性的放逐 而西裡爾....
...took control of the power in Alexandria.
則掌握了亞歷山大的大權
Later, Cyril was declared a Saint and Doctor of the Church.
不久之後 西裡爾被封為聖徒 教會聖士
Although not any of Hipatia works remains,
盡管希帕蒂婭的成果 沒有被保存下來
it is known that she was an exceptional astronomer,
但她仍然被後人當作傑出的天文學家
well-known for the mathematical study of conical curves.
並且以對圓錐曲線的研究而著稱
One thousand, two hundred years later,
1200年後
in the 17th century, astronomer Johannes Kepler...
17世紀 天文學家約翰內斯?開普勒
...described that one of those curves,...
解釋了圓錐曲線之中的
...the ellipse, governs the movement of the planets.
橢圓 正是它主宰著星球的運動軌跡